all right welcome to this week's game be
idea cafe the question we are all
answering today or passing on which I
sometimes forget to mention as an option
is how do you think we transition to
game B so I just like to there is no
right or wrong answer it's just what you
individually feel is the best course of
action because usual or no course of
action I guess if that's what it calls
to you so as always I would David's your
team that in David and David alright
would anybody like to start I'm always
willing to start if nobody else would
like to I don't mind starting I mean I
to be honest how do we transition to
game B as always the question I get
stuck on as has come up a couple of
times in previous conversations with
some of you guys so I guess I'm just
gonna take a minute I'm not going to use
the whole five minutes I'm just going to
take one minute just to talk about the
whole Trek that notion of transition to
game B because I how can I put this
feels as though the phrase transition to
game be move means moving from one game
structure to another game structure and
this the this still troubles me again
this has come up a couple of times
before but this still troubles me
because that feels like a retooling of
game a kinda thing because gay game be
at least my understanding about this is
this is very personal like my
understanding of it is that it is a meta
game that it's not a game in itself but
that it's a framework if you like it's
not the perfect word but a framework
within if you like within which all of
the games that we are going to play in
order to solve problems in order to you
know have people living harmoniously
with each other
fed clothed house watered etc you know
all of that stuff will emerge from game
B but it is not game B and so that's
that's really I think all I want to say
is that the idea of transiting to game B
as though game B is a thing a place you
know which can be defined and and and we
can go to I I still have trouble with
that whole notion with that whole sort
of set of vocabulary that's that's
that's it that's my piece
I forgot to mute myself who would like
to go next second just unmute myself
when the people can raise their hand so
I have to unmute and remute everybody
who would like to go next
I'll go transience find next I'll go
really really you know in order to
transition I guess to a game B first you
have to define what that game B is in by
defined specifically I mean you have to
have a clear understanding of all you
know who controls all the resources of
the world combines them produces things
distributes how things are distributed
access etcetera so once you have a anew
I guess a game what the rules are who's
controlling what and what the purposes
are what the rules of engagement and how
we're going to distribute all these
things and and have this new
relationship together then we can talk
about the transition how to get from
where we are today to game B so once
that's defined then the transition I
suppose could be beginning so we're
still stuck I think on trying to I think
define this game B specifically as to
what it is exactly that we're trying to
build and get to I'll stop there for now
we can continue the conversation
afterwards all right David or Brent
either of you like to go yes just raise
your hands and all right go ahead David
all right thanks microphones okay sounds
okay so I think that room Z what you
said this serves something for me in
that I I'm not sure that we can define
define it in a way to make a transition
from they made it game B and I and I
understand the desire to do that I think
more in terms of I think what Bucky
fuller said about transitioning is is
very apt that creating a new way that
makes the old way obsolete is important
rather than trying to make changes to
the existing to the existent phenomena
strategy but I think that that is
challenging what I'm noticing right now
as I pay attention to the various
podcasts the speakers the writers who
are
seem to be picking up on a common theme
is that the kinds of challenges that
we're running into you right now speak
to people individually in a way that has
us wanting to unite and yet there's
something that feels contentious our
rival risk and how we go about it so one
of the things that I think is important
is finding ways to merge our efforts
without having to necessarily agree on
all of the rules
I like I like a maked Derulo megha
because it's not so much a playing it's
kind of a meta rule right it is a it's a
way of engaging such that we actually
listen to each other and kind of discern
what the underlying needs are there but
in the progress the feedback loops that
are necessary in order to see our we're
making progress it gets a little bit
messy but I think that part of the issue
is trying to think that there is a
strategic way for us to lay out on a map
and be able to get there that way I
think is problematic and leads to
contingence ways of thinking about it
they're not
would you like to go or would you like
me to go I'll go I liked what you said
about Jubilee there not being any right
or wrong answers of course that's key
today and just expressing ourselves but
I think there are some right or right
and wrong answers around this issue and
you know in a friendly way I'd say that
you're all wrong
to some extent because there's too much
uncertainty there um so hopefully I can
I can propose some more determined paths
to to this transition because there's a
lot of systems change literature over
time you know over the past you know
half century and whatnots but also very
recently right and timing-wise there's a
lot more convergence of late so you know
year and a half ago two years ago is the
UN report that said we had 12 years to
you know find a collective action
solution to this kind of runaway climate
change that is anthropogenic and you
know it's it's a part of a kind of
political systems failure as well right
if we can't coordinate on it then then
it's just going to get worse and it's
not that the world is gonna end in 12
years it's that we have 10 years now we
have a window to coordinate and this is
unprecedented right so this is one kind
of historical marker that says like we
we have to do systems change and systems
changes have happened before
but this is a new global context and me
several of my projects recently have
been on systems transitions and kind of
intersecting literature's there so
there's a lot there right and and so
we've got the we've got the the kind of
plans and templates and we've also got
the time horizon you know the window of
opportunity mm-hmm and so there's a lot
I could say about that but I want to
also shift to two politics because
there's a sense in which you know
politics and culture are kind of
decoupled or parallel or one overtakes
other to influence the course of history
I don't like the notion that you know
like like Steve ban and likes to say
that the politics is downstream from
culture I don't think it's so
unidirectional you know it's more
complicated than that
mm-hmm but but you know by some measures
you know politics is kind of
inconsequential there's a huge lag
behind progress and we're just it's just
kind of piecemeal progress there's a lot
of compromise and satisficing and we get
what we get right but every once in a
while you have a kind of system change
type candidate and there's elections you
know eminent in the in the UK and the US
and so it matters who you elect right
and there's been a lot of talk about
this over the past four years and in my
view there's only one kind of systems
change can that's Bernie Sanders right
you're not going to get any immediate
transition or actions towards gain be
with you know p-put agender or Elizabeth
Warren or a Amy Klobuchar whoever and
the media is still pumping up these
alternative candidates and and and and
various degrees they have money backing
them right making them look more viable
than they are mean but you know the the
Bernie Sanders movement as a whole it's
not just about him it's it's actually
the biggest mass progressive movement
right so there's there's this pressure
to sort of fall in line but wait but you
can't coerce people right it has to be
kind of attractive based on you know
positive ideas but you know systems
change is explicitly part of Bernie's
platform through something like the
green new deal and and many other things
he said but I think it's also an
implicit factor and that it's open-ended
and it's going to be reflexive and it's
going to be
you know we can have set plans for the
next decade but it's also going to be
changeable and contingent and you know
were ostensibly all going to be involved
in helping manage that process cuz it's
gonna take a decade right but I think I
think we're on on the cusp of that
decade right 2020 is coming up and we've
got to make the right decisions in all
sectors right in in the political
revolution in kind of changing social
consciousness and environmentalism etc
so I do think we need to get on the same
page there quickly and that's that's
five minutes myself awesome thanks Brent
I don't know if I'll be taking five
minutes but one of the reasons like this
is our third idea Cafe on game B and so
we did talk about what our definition of
game B was and why we want to game B and
so this is a bit weird of a conversation
to have without actually I've had to you
having had that conversation but I also
think that if we wait until we have a
definitive we all agreed on what game B
is to transition we don't we it's really
hard to agree on that especially when
it's this this we all live in game a
we're all in competition and we don't
even know how the ways we're all
competing to know how to let that go to
create an omni win anti rival risk
solution so to me my definition of game
a is basically capitalism is this forced
sense of competition that you either
participate in or you starve and so my
definition of game B is a voluntary
organized cooperation system that runs
parallel to the current one and does
transition us to game B by voluntary I
mean every step along the way if we
don't have a better food system than
what game is offering you you're not
going to come on board for anything
we're offering in the parallel system if
we don't have a better technology our
social network social media platform
that you want to participate in in and
beyond you're going to be on Facebook
you're going to be on Twitter so every
step along the way is voluntary do you
want your data to be used in this way
and organized is how we have our
individual contributions without
actually move us in the direction
towards game-game be my solution the
thing that I do think gets us to game be
is a technology cooperative so we are
all bringing together our our resources
our money our passion our to move us in
one direction which never takes power
over our individual lives but only gives
us the tools to be able to have personal
sovereignty how I think we control the
system as a whole together like politics
and economics a little bit we ignore it
before to create the tools about
collaboration but then we information is
so powerful that when you have trust
where each trustworthy transparent
information on our politicians they
don't have the amount of overreaching
power they currently have when you can
see what they voted for in the past they
can't spin it right now the information
so complex that it's understandable that
people act like old fish or we're only
looking at the moment but when you can
actually break it down and show people
what in Bernie Sanders vote for in the
past compared to Donald Trump who only
has a track record for this to past
three years but with economics if you
can show people what they're putting in
their bodies is good or bad for them the
planet the people they're going to make
better choices but without ever
demanding that things be put into
anything that isn't absolutely
ridiculous not to have into law like no
murder no sexual assault no clearly
taking somebody else's property
everything else needs to be done on a
sovereign basis if like if I want you to
do something how do I help you do it if
I want you to not buy the thing that's
gonna destroy us all how do I fill that
need for you without it destroying us
all and so that to me is how we
transition to game B is to create the
tools to truly listen to each other and
listen to what we need and not live it
up to our governments we're not going to
be able to solve it because they're not
designed to make the massive change on
the rapid weight in the on the time
scale we need and deal with
repercussions at the same time that
we're going to create together and not
ever leaving it up to a tiny group of
people to have obscene amounts of
knowledge that other people don't have
power that other people don't have it's
like do you want to participate in
creating the tools you get to come
participate in creating tools if you
just want to use the tools just use the
tools you get to choose how involved you
are and so that is how I think we
transition to gaming and now we can
unmute everyone and have an open
conversation
oh sorry David they were both try to
unmute you I cannot meet you David maybe
only you kinam there you go um I'd like
to start by just there are a lot of what
you just said I like they
technologically based cooperative makes
sense to me I also um I would like to
extend it by thinking it's um
distributed and decentralized in
holographic in nature meaning
practically sized to the appropriate
problems being solved in the community
that solving it so it doesn't
necessarily have to be universally
applied across the entire spectrum of
the of the cooperative in order for it
to be effective that one group wants to
try something and share what the results
are that makes sense the other thing
that I like about that approach is then
we're not so much in competition if
somebody comes and says I want to join
your coop but I want to do it this way
is they actually you know the place
where that's really being done is over
here let's help you find the place
that's most resonant with the kinds of
problems and the methods that you want
to achieve and get involved in that way
and if you're finding it there's no
place that matches but let's check the
entire cooperative is there any are
there other people who see this variant
that's variation that we want to want to
try something new so there's a way in
which it can more organically and
responsibly deal with problems and
approaches rather than trying to deal
with it universally top-down so I like I
like that inertia and with that
additional and the flavor of it mm-hmm I
do like the idea of a lot of the jisub
platforms my issue with most of them is
they can't how they're currently being
done they cannot out-compete game a
because they're not accessible
intellectually to most people they're
not except like I can't jump on board
and be part of one of the whole chain
projects without understanding
technology on a whole new level that I
don't and they don't really want to hear
that it's too complex like well sort of
like it's not that I like what you said
when someone comes on board that's the
point it's like there's room for
everyone
this is Omni win if you come on board
and help us why wouldn't we want you
there and so to be able to help everyone
find their space is I think like one of
the huge goals of a technology
cooperative including that yeah it's not
decentralizing just to say it's
decentralized and it's not centralizing
just to centralize it it's like what
makes the most sense right it makes
sense to have one Facebook like entity
that we're all on so we can like use
that as the for the tools for everything
else but it doesn't make sense if it's
gonna take away your autonomy right if
you have to follow certain rules to be
on there it's going to limit your free
speech it's going to limit your access
to information you're not gonna want to
be there and so creating it in a way
that we're listening to individuals but
efficiently creating for the whole and
there'll be knitting stains that are
gonna be very powerful for small groups
of people that are part of what we want
to create together
cani cani so sorry Ramsey you go ahead I
was just gonna I'm just gonna try and
offer a little frame to continue the
discussion in yes I'm I think we all we
all expressed a sort of inability or
unwillingness or whatever to clarify
exactly what game B is right and that I
think it was David made the point that
you know you can't map out a transition
to something when you don't know what
the thing is that you're transitioning
towards when you'd have a clearer idea
with your transition sports and so you
know get given that fact and honoring
that fact right you know not trying well
we have to come up with it we have to
come up with a definition right because
we need a transition plan you know
rather than that the idea of small-scale
experimentation was was popping into my
head on more than one occasion as you
guys were speaking you know they're
creating somehow and I'm not I don't
have a clear picture of this but somehow
or other
creating a playing field and environment
in which small-scale experiments because
there's a billion ideas out there right
I mean every day there's 20 new post
people coming up with idea for this
without the other right and so you know
I I think a great way of managing the
transition towards game B would be to
create spaces in which experiments could
be run on these things and that you know
learning from the successes and failures
of those experiments that what game B
actually is going to become might also
become clearer as a consequence of
running those experiments you see what I
mean and so the the map and the
destination become clearer at the same
time as you run the small experiments
either does that sound like a reasonable
way you know in broad strokes of
approaching it um I just wanted to say
we don't have much historical context in
which to look at you know revolutions or
transitions in the past because let's be
honest every single revolution or
transition in the past has been from one
game a to another so there is not much
for us to look at there now if we can
all agree at least for most of us here
hopefully that the definition of the
defining feature of game a is it you
know the control and ownership of
resources for either asset appreciation
or asked you know or value extraction
and so with that particular game of
people owning things so they can either
hoard them so that they can increase in
value or to extract the value from the
resources by combining resources and
labor etc that's game a so whatever game
B that we propose if you're playing that
same game then it's still game a so this
is why what I'm saying is is that if we
have a clear understanding of who owns
what because if at any transition from
the past in the country which I was born
they went through multiple transitions
essentially they were all from game a a
game a of course but they redefined
slightly that the rules and who owned
what and so they redistributed a
reallocated resources land etc
it divided the land amongst all of the
villagers and communities and so they
did that we don't we don't we need to do
that again today by the way on a global
level because we don't have equal access
to actual physical resources and the
fake resources called money so clearly
there needs to be some type of a
property redistribution and
understanding of who's gonna own what
but not necessarily own it per se but
essentially be caretaker of it because
remember we don't want to play the same
game as game a we don't want to own
things and hold resources control
resources access them for the purposes
of trying to act like you know create
maximum value it should be different
game there so should be for value
creation like what Jubilees mentioning
rather than if they value extraction so
that would require a different type of
economics to incentivize that game as
well but to Julie's point you know I
believe it can be done there was a group
of people you know in the technocracy
movement who started that over a hundred
years ago and who are the same kind of
you know thinking we can organize these
things using technology and new
applications but they just didn't have
the full technology tool that we have
today to be able to I think develop
further their ideas but the transition I
believe is going to be to a game be has
to be peaceful
they can't it's not going to be by
competing our competing game a but
rather attracting people who want to
play the new game versus the shit game
that we're playing now so I think it's
going to be more of an attractor that
whereas here's the technology here's the
tools here's the game that we would like
to play you know do you want to play
with us you know you can become a member
whatever and then we can develop develop
that transition etc so that's how I'm
imagining the transition I think it's
going to take time for more of us to
develop it but it's gonna come piecemeal
once the tools become more readily
available and more people are engaged in
this discussion I think things will
become more crystallized will begin to
you know to input the data for the
property and for the resources
so we have those tools in place and
understanding of who owns what but then
we can change the game
I like your leg which is much more
diplomatic when I say out-compete I mean
that I mean creating an attractor that
is so attractive that people have a
choice for every individual project
product service community do you want
game a or do you want game B right or
this parallel system that is maybe
transition game B and then they if if
it's better for them as an individual
they're gonna choose game B and
eventually if there's no one else
playing game a it out completes it it
does it does take it away I don't agree
about the resources that that is game B
I don't necessarily agree that that is
how we transition because those things
are already owned by people and anytime
that's kind of a is the communist part
of like going in and taking over the
means of production I the the
information piece I absolutely agree
with just having that information about
who owned leaves what and how it is
moves around the globe is very powerful
and that is the kind of thing we can
create now with technology that helps us
figure that piece out but I don't think
we just switch over to a new system
because it's not playing the small
experiments it's it's it can be a
catastrophic failure on a massive scale
if we just have all the sudden even if
it's utopia and this brand-new system
because we don't know all of the ways
that we as individuals play in that
system creating it piecemeal where it's
um you know did we create a better a
better coca-cola did we create a better
Facebook did we create is that the
answers in did people choose it over the
other one or is there something more
offering them and then when we offer
them the tools for massive collaboration
I think people a lot of people not
everyone but a lot of people choose to
come and collaborate they choose to come
and give their passion and energy to
something they can see has a hope in
creating a better world for themselves
for their communities for the world and
the more we offer that the better and
that's how we get charged with it
resources eventually so I think one of
the things that's important is looking
at the way that that we approach this in
a
yes and approach so what I heard you say
Julie sounded like it was in contrast to
what room she was saying and it doesn't
necessarily need to be isn't property
property redistribution can be done on a
gradual practical basis rather than all
at once
it's not a matter of saying okay we're
unfinished we're gonna change to this
model its people I have property I can I
can join that and figure out how to
bring that in and the distribution of
that and how does that work out and I
think that it's there's an interesting
notion of this that the visual that
comes to mind for me is the difference
from moving from marching band type
commanded control
let's do this in a structured way to a
murmuration of starlings you know
flocking and flowing together that kind
of behavior really requires very high
levels of attunement individually in
feedback systems within the group to see
kind of what's happening we have to be
able to have that kind of thing to give
them to do that and I don't think we're
gonna be able to do a switch overall
from one to the other but small
experiments of that kind of flocking can
then grow and you can sort of see
because different experiments are
working differently as we're sharing
information with each other I think that
that part that's that's really
interesting is thinking about changing
the notion of the way that intellectual
property and privacy works I don't think
that again that that's an overall thing
everywhere but that one of the main
things that I think game G practitioners
are engaged in is what are these methods
and models that work on and more
feedback on this kind of a feedback
method that allow us to fly is it
working is it working over here is it
not looking over there why is it not
just really noticing the kinds of things
that work experimenting that and being
able to flesh it out and throw it thank
you David I'd love that especially I'm
just going to talk about 30 seconds that
the that I'm saying know as opposed to
yes end and that end of itself is the
flock because it's like the
instantaneous feedback on that right
versus allowing that to continue or I
don't know
I just wanted to say thank you and and
yes yes and yes let's get resources and
control and create the technology and do
it all yep can I also say as well source
also climb back to something David said
very very much in line with my own
thinking on this that things like rule
Omega R that is that's kind of game B
essence right there right that's the
holy water of game B because that's
that's not it's not a thing it's not a
structure it's not a set of well it kind
of is a set of rules but it's not rules
in that sense it's it's a methodology by
which one can more fully utilize the
resources available to come to better
decisions better perspectives whatever
and so that kind of meta the development
of those meta type protocols that's
another powerful transitional tool right
because you know the game the new game
will emerge from things like that right
without needing to define what it is it
will emerge naturally by a sufficient
number of people embodying things like
that so again I think it's a another
powerful transitional idea any any idea
don't offend you can think of any other
examples rule Omega is top of my list
certainly MVC has a lot of I was talking
to Roland is I don't know if any of you
had any interaction with Roland Eze I
was talking to him about rule Omega and
MVC and he's really into MVC and he was
going through some of the principles and
some of the ideas and they're very very
very closely aligned I mean I think
there's definitely bridges to to be
built between the communities there yeah
I had a brief interaction with Roland as
he was on one of these the Communist
Marxism one and also Hugh I had
mentioned yes I've heard of non-violent
communication but basically that I've
just watched an hour-long
talk twice the same the same talk a few
months apart and I think you're right
that there is a lot of non-violent
communication is about getting
everybody's needs met and if it feels
like we're in conflict there's generally
a way we can get our needs met and if
we're bypassing someone's needs that's
never good like it always has negative
consequences even if it's a little
datta's polite or what is supposed to be
done in society it has an underlining
consequence that when people's
boundaries are crossed and their needs
aren't being met that we need to be able
to figure figure out and that and rule
Omega I think are kind of the the dance
of game of game B and figuring that out
personally of like okay how do I yes and
and how do i how do we create how do we
have everyone working in their direction
of what they think the next step is and
having it lead somewhere as a whole that
it gets us somewhere do you guys think
that the transition would be more
difficult or easier if we have an
upcoming economic chaos I'm not
suggesting collapse or depression
because that takes time but what I'm
thinking is going to happen next year is
probably going to be volatility in terms
of asset fluctuations of the stock
markets of other commodities of
currencies etc which is going to cause
disruptions in and of course to collapse
and bankruptcies for certain industries
and corporations etc because
corporations in you know can't handle
uncertainty they need to have constant
cash flow etc so when when we if we have
a economic chaos coming up is it going
to be easier for us to transition is
that going to make it assuming that we
have a game B plan of course it's in
motion or is it going to make it more
difficult and lead us towards some kind
of authoritarian fascist you know
martial law shit so either way
absolutely could go either way on it and
I think it depends in part on the way of
transitions and I want to answer that
briefly and then I'd like to ask Brent
the way in so what I'll say is I think
that if we prepare for that with an
awareness of what sorts of transitions
are possible like at the moment of like
starting to get the kind of feedback of
power things working do we think there's
going to be a collapse or a correction
and if so what are these responses
the correction of the work while doing
some sort of initial thought pending
before it happens will be easier than
saying oh that collapse that we happen
to have a tragedy right now you know the
way that I like to dig about this is it
if thumb is a dad's driving down the
mountain path and in all of a sudden the
road gets icy that's not the time to
pull out the map it's a hey Dad let's
look at the map and see which way is the
best way to go that's really no there's
no time for planning at that point the
time for looking at what does the
landscape what are our possible avenues
for development is now when things are
relatively calm then as it unrolls let's
really revisit than update America but I
wanted to take it to you Brenda
specifically because it seems that your
initial statement was the most distinct
from the kind of collective view in
terms of going towards Bernie Sanders as
the independent and looking into quickly
I'm curious what you've heard so far and
kind of specifically what rooms he said
how where are you now yeah based on that
last question first I think you know we
can't predict what the economy is gonna
do in that sense and it it kind of
doesn't matter in terms of our you know
decision matrix because like for me it's
clear what policies we should be
supporting you know things like the
green New Deal and like there's
something called simple simultaneous
policy and that's a kind of coordination
effort for international convergence on
on on policies could have a new level of
meta governance and and like I said with
all the systems transition literature
like a lot of it is spelled out in quite
clear detail like where we're headed
where we need to go and how to get there
and where we're headed if we don't so as
for the economic crisis or depression or
whatever it may be like that's gonna
affect different people differently of
course it's not really a cause for
concern is for us if the corporation
goes out of business if that's what it's
destined to do you know we can't be
bailing out banks for example right you
know instead of a
putting that money to better use the
other general comment that would make is
you know there's this kind of sentiment
and mmm interest in bottom-up organizing
and experimenting and that's super
important but I would say that you know
society itself is an experiment and it
contains tons of social experiments
every type of Association is a kind of
form of collective intelligence and has
some purpose to effect some change of
the landscape and so over the past
century there's been a ton of
experimentation in in this progressive
vein right with with with things like
communes and I always think back to this
documentary all watched over by machines
of loving grace it's Adam Curtis
documentary and it's about basically
these intentional communities and
communes of the of the 70s that really
have the right progressive ideas but
ultimately a lot of them fell apart
because they didn't adequately any
factor in power as part of the equation
right so they were attempting to set up
a kind of game B system but it still was
subject to realism and and and various
dynamics that threaten the integrity of
a progressive steady state so we have
these lessons from the past and not
every lesson is clear like why it failed
right sometimes it's just an example of
capitalism crushing a kind of democratic
socialist experiment somewhere in the
world like like all over Latin America
for example um so we've we can learn a
lot from that but my final point would
be that you know all this bottom-up
organizing and you know heuristics for
for for a positive interaction and
whatnot non-religious dynamics it's not
worth anything if it's not coordinated
with the top-down change as well and
there's so much happening at the top
right with elite factionalism and and
just a lot a lot of things shift you
know a lot a lot more prominent people
coming public with critiques of elite
finance and philanthropy we need you
know
eat people need to get real about what
their what their negative impact has
been and how they can affect a positive
future and so the bottom up in the
talked about organizing and change has
to be coordinated or else or else it's
all for nothing right because if you
have a bunch of enthusiastic bottom up
people that themselves get into power
and don't know what to do it'll fall
apart and and vice versa if you have
elites manipulating the masses you know
so someone like you know people judge
becomes president by chance and it's you
know he's not the progressive people
thought he was it's it's gonna fall
apart
so you need that alignment and
convergence between what we're doing
with bottom-up organizing and what what
the top-down potential for change has
been converging towards for the past 50
years like the potential tipping point
right because the the paradigm were in
getting more specific than gaming right
the last 4050 years its characterized by
neoliberalism in a very distinct way and
so there's there's built-in
rules to that game that that undermine
progress and gain the protocols right so
that that needs to change to you know
something more common space but without
you know there's something more close
capitalist but without completely
appending the you know without
collectivizing people's private
resources right it needs to be adjusted
and written I mean I like a lot of that
and there's some there's some parts that
um that I would tweak one one thing that
I hear in that that I that I don't agree
with that I'd like to look at a little
detail is the way in which the bottom up
and the top-down court in some way I
don't think because the bottom up
effectively is if we consider can be
primarily coming from bottom-up it
doesn't have enough power and authority
to
really get the interest of the of the
elites and in some way I think more like
loving or hating Elon Musk has done
something in terms of moving towards
electric cars which is an emo no way is
there anybody going to say yeah let's
find a system that way a governmental
way of doing that he's just doing a
free-market way I'm going to move in
this direction and he's starting to move
the needle on his own yeah that's a good
thing but I don't I don't think that's
true that it's only going to come from
private innovation like it's kind of
calm you know public knowledge to some
extent that that industry has been you
know actively suppressed and held back
and in the u.s. especially there's been
a lot of like like lack of a progressive
governance right so they could have
chosen to an actually government plays a
really important role in this idea of a
big push economically of changing
systems they just haven't done it it
doesn't mean that we have to and should
leave it to people like Elon Musk right
yeah so I agree I think and that's kind
of the point is Elon Musk didn't wait
for right but the progressive push from
above is like a you know forget it I'm
just gonna go and not everybody can do
that so there is both but it doesn't
require that that's the starting point
there's also a notion that I have but I
heard somebody say and actually it's
first to make more sense but it seemed
nonsensical at first
somebody said collapse early avoid the
rush you know we're already heading
there finding people that's sort of this
sense of the starting of a game the
network cooperative experiment let's do
this you know the people who are
interested in really committed and
finding a way to do that don't wait for
somebody else to give permission
demonstrate that it works and then
started acting more interested in that
way but it's a it's a really interesting
kind of initiative how to do that how to
do sort of collective decision-making
that isn't I'd like to add one more
thing is oh no this is
being a little bit more complicated a
model that I think that was the way that
the neurons work in a brain it really is
that fractal holographics since making
apparatus and rather than trying to
think of you don't have every neuron
coding on every decision each neuron has
a very specific very tuned way of
thinking you know caring about what's
going on with it's 10,000 connections
and very it's a very tightly managed
internal sense making or what's
important it's not based on a higher
view of propositional notions it really
is a and some level such a local
decision that it's nuanced by something
very minor and then it's aggregated in a
way that gives the sense of where what
is where is the sense in the system and
so there's something that I I think that
we can develop things like that neural
net infrastructure is similar to that
and I think that we can really do
something to allow human beings to see
that and really hone what is your
specific flavor that you care about and
how is that reacting to your your local
and then the global sense right so
there's some interesting models there
but I think that are interesting to
start moving in the direction of this
what I'm having to do it top-down all I
see it exactly the way you just
described the David the art I think the
dysfunction that we have in today's
system in this game a is that just like
that neural network
you've got did you call it a molecule or
so whatever it doesn't matter the
individual in this neural network that
contains millions or billions the
problem with him existing dynamic is
that one cell is able to control and
make decisions instantaneously for
millions and billions of the other cells
without taking input in allowing the
individual cells to form the cohesive to
have their say and to control the
direction like a flock of starlings
start what would you go it's the same
thing but this is the description of
top-down economics that we have today
you know one person controls this supply
of oil the supply of gold or this supply
of wheat etc and so without any input
from you know below besides this
arbitrary you know price mechanism that
we pretend is in all all seeing in all
comes and but it's actually not the
people control the resources ultimately
are making decisions that are not taking
all the rest of the stakeholders into
place so we have a dysfunction of one
cell making billions of decisions for
others I mean negating us that's a
cancer but you know in our body if one
cell had that power we would take that
can't they sell out because it's it's
it's benefiting itself in its group but
to the detriment of our entire host and
this is kind of what capitalism is doing
today it the the corporations to their
individual benefit are winning but at
the cost of potentially destroying the
host that you know us individual players
need the rest of us need also to survive
so that's that's it exactly what you
just like I think I'm the bottom-up
approach is for me anyway finding how to
have that type of interconnection with a
small group of people and it growing and
like growing systematically where every
new person that comes in is adding their
piece of that neural network is adding
their connections their dot other
information and when we can figure it
out including what's not working and
what's working for 10,000 people it's
not that hard to get to 20,000 it's not
that hard to get to 40,000 right like
it's and from that space and we figure
out how to make it work for a million
people we're not gonna let our
governments have this top-down authority
over us because we're like like right
now we're like what else is there we
need a centralized idea who we think
have better knowledge than we do to run
our countries and to run our countries
together with global efficiency when
they clearly don't know what the eff is
going on like they clearly are they're
working in their own self-interest and
they don't have perfect knowledge
whereas if we can figure out how to run
out
our lives and create the tools to be
able to you know have my connection with
my people and have my my needs met my
food on my table a roof over my head as
well as the information I need to do the
the art I want to do the creation I want
to do the inventions I want to do having
like my own little piece of the world
work and having it work in
interconnection with other people we're
not going to put up with this top-down
approach and we can truly showcase that
bottom-up works and that we'd like what
it's kind of coordinating with top-down
but not because they're kind of a little
bit ignoring it until they're just like
yeah that's not working we can show that
yes and we actually can create solutions
that work with a million people once we
can do that Pierce just real quick the
cold how many people are following John
grab a key in detail Toronto a scientist
who's doing some of that I'm at pepper
episode 1516 something I'm watching here
I'm well behind the eight-ball but I am
watching them they're brilliant no I
mean everyone should watch them they're
brilliant I think he's providing he's
providing a vocabulary for people to
actually discuss transformative
experience in the culture broadly I mean
I think he's making he's making a
massive contribution look back in a
hundred years I think he's gonna be one
of the mains we look back on as being
instrumental in the transformation of
society as if assuming we do manage to
transform agree that's and that's kind
of the good thing that I see is that
he's bringing together a common
vocabulary that allows us to have some
conversations that in the reason I ask
in particular it's because there's one
of the notions that he mentions is the
difference between propositional knowing
and put down or knowing you know levels
of knowing are very different and I
mentioned it also because there's
something that we were just talking
about here about the extractive model so
my thought is this is my own thinking
and I'm looking for ways to see if this
is true is that extractive models and
hierarchical systems work well when
there's a surplus when there's plenty to
it extract
that is the most orderly way to get the
most extraction value button that's
running low either the cost of
externalization is too high or the cost
of extraction is too high and it starts
to break down it really moves back into
a different kind of model of the
organizational that looks like the
murmuration of starlings it looks like
but more neuron mode but I'm one to the
other especially when we've been you
know do we have I would disagree that
being a is capitalism
I'd say game a is extracted it's
everything back to agriculture the
belief that we can modify the
environment to suit our needs and we
kind of continue to find ways to do that
we're now you know this is what Jordan
Hall in danish mike burgers like we're
now at a point where the we can't do
that easily we might possibly create
very slim chance that we might possibly
be able to double down one more time and
find a way to continue the game a model
and input off the the answer to the next
transition but i don't think it is i
think that there's out of that
overwhelming sense that that's not true
or that you know at that best it's you
know half and half but we're now at that
point where we have to transition back
to hierarchy doesn't make sense anymore
the challenge is we've been doing that
for so long than the thought that the
kings that what they do that that one
person can speak for millions is
effective is kind of ingrained in our
system in a way that we have to reject
that and so it's it it makes it
acknowledging that gives me compassion
for those who don't see this you know
it's a way of actually hearing me lent
allowing me to offer a bit of rule omega
listening to people who think that that
capitalism was best and that game a is
continually successful i can see why you
think so but we really have to feel into
what's the present moment was too
stressed attack why is mediate you know
all of our institutions are crumbling so
how do we you know they're on the verge
of collapse
how do we actually address that in a
nice to know so I think that this I
think there is something in there that
will be persuasive maybe not for the
hardcore gain a people but for the
fringe and I think it's something that
becomes some more of an attractor for
the people who are on the edge who are
like like it's just too complex I can't
help difference that starts to speak I
think more sense in a way this is oh
yeah that actually makes sense in my
bones
I mean it's it's deeper even than
extractive or exploitative /
profiteering well I think the concepts
of rival risk Ness is deeper still than
any of that right I'd like to come back
to something Brent said a little while
ago in the context of rival resinous
because you know the minimizing rival
this richness and maximizing anti rival
business is right at the heart of game
be thinking right I'm interested in what
you said before Brent about you know for
example commune experiments that have
been tried essentially living game B
valleys if you want to call them that
but that they broke down because of you
you alluded to the idea of power I'm
assuming what you mean by that was
people seeking power over others within
that collective in some way or another
right and so are you saying that that
even when you are in a non rival hrus
environment in that you're not competing
for food and so on right this is all
this is all you know part of the
collective endeavor that even within
that kind of playing field rival
richness over power still manifests
itself is that what you're saying yeah
from what I recall
so you just just before just before you
answer can I just add one more part of
the question though are you saying that
that is an inevitable part of human
nature or could that be put down to the
fact that the people that entered those
communes grew up in rivalry environment
and had learned that behavior from a
very very young age that's that's the
end of my question yeah it can be both
from what I remember of the documentary
that was the thesis basically that you
know whether it's human nature or people
were just socialized into game a yeah
power dynamics and you know wanting to
be a leader or whatever kind of
distorted certain functionality of it so
it's it's an important documentary to
revisit and you know to think of all of
these social experiments that way yeah I
think you know like technology is
constantly changing too so the the issue
of
the topic of post-scarcity is more you
know salient and achievable so we can
kind of put some of these dynamics and
check the other thing is if there is
human nature seeking power you know we
need to sublimate that into other
activities whether it's sports or
whatever it's like you know you do it in
a conscious participatory way without
you know it has it has a safety net
there's not a risk of dying for example
in a competitive sport you're just in it
for love of love of the game and love of
kind of pure competition right within a
certain rule structure so it can be
healthy so you know whatever game B
turns out to be obviously people need to
be able to opt in to game a types of
dynamics for the the generativity that
they have but it needs to be hot you
know for lack of a better word regulated
right because what we have now is not
just capitalism like it's extremely
unfettered capitalism a lot of the the
extraction that we talk about it wealth
is very very abstract like it's all just
on paper it's you know algorithms moving
moving numbers around and it's you know
there's there's a very selfish aspects
to this that people are just enriching
themselves and it's it's undermining the
entire global system right so this is
something we all have to reconcile with
elites especially but yeah this idea of
extraction like it's it's way more
prevalent than people think
I think it's just this is this is the
central pathology of late-stage
capitalism it's not it's not just
finance but it's every extractive
industry that there's no kind of
conscience about how those resources
trickle down through the company or
through the society you know it cost 50
peanuts go for a piss in a train station
in London 50 P to take a piss in the
train station a public train say what
what are your choices yeah it's pretty
absurd and and the implication of that
too is if you're gonna put a little kind
of Norma
be on it you know how much further does
it go do you have cops on the payroll
that enforced that they go around and
humiliate people and and target less
privileged people right it's a slippery
slope so we need to have a kind of a
systemic consciousness that doesn't
implement policies like that in the
first place like and you got to keep in
mind that that policy very well may have
been the outcome of some focus group or
or consultation that made it seem like a
good idea
it's a beautiful notion and I actually
like that quite a bit that I do want to
watch the can you say the name of the
talking about we've all watched over by
machines of loving grace it's a mouthful
of a title but I I would I would say
check out all of Adam curtis's work
right his latest documentary want to say
be tough on us knows that pretend yeah
hyper normalization it's just it's not
so I wanted to say that there is a you
know one of the things that I that I
typically do is I think of metaphors and
think of systemic behavior and I agree I
think it's not so much extractive it is
rival risk but I actually think that
it's um it's and I'm gonna say that I
think it's an evolutionary tendency I
think it's actually a law of
thermodynamics to some extent in this
way that when there's a surplus and the
best way to get to that is with a
hierarchical structure that in some way
what happens in that mode is authority
as externalized it does make sense to
have a king or a father or God an
external authority figure that we're all
following those rules and mandates for
we're following them in a to the letter
kind of a mode in that the whole of
civilization with literacy and alphabet
and numeracy and organization and laws
does organize under this very powerful
external authority model which if I
think of within a family unit the father
the patriarch moley this is the
direction that we're going in the
children are rival risk right the
sibling rivalry is a fight for the
available resources and
necessary to be able to grow they need
to be as greedy as it can to grow to a
healthy adult but in a mode where that
surplus is no longer available when the
children grow to adult it rivalry in
that way does it make they need to
switch into an adult mode in which
they're actually working together and
that's what I think the game D model I
actually think that it's not even game a
and game B in terms of grab reversal not
harvest I think it actually is something
more like appropriate regulation to the
way of responding to our environmental
needs and our internal needs as we go
I'll give an example that I think is
really beautiful illustration of that in
the movie march of the Penguins number
of years ago as Morgan Freeman is
describing their activity one of the
things he notices is as the Penguins are
marching to their mating ground you have
two moves
they're either marching in a straight
line or the occasionally will huddle
when they seem to be lost the no window
huddle collectively sort of vibrating
until they know collectively with the
direction and now they go into a line
mode again and so that's the most
efficient way if we continue to go in a
line then they're lost they're sure to
die if they continue to huddle past the
point to know where they're going
they'll die it's an appropriate scaling
as moving quickly or moving slowly and
in some way I would say the analogy is
moving in a line is high as hierarchical
extracted
let's move bathroom how to do this when
there's uncertainty and that there's a
friction in the line the fractal node
you know we could tell oh how do we know
we're lost
it's not one person is something of the
sense of the line is we don't know where
we're going and it collapses into a
huddle and that model I think I'm taking
a back to the idea of neurons
I think expresses what Daniel Kahneman
distinguishes between system one baking
and system 2 thinking system 1 thinking
is the heuristic let's move fast we have
some we have a good enough idea to apply
this we don't need to refigure out this
everything we don't have have to invent
calculus just apply apply calculus when
we're lost
ok hold on a second we need to invent
new mathematics we need to slow laid
figure out what the challenge is and
again I don't think if you do that on a
global scale all at once but finding
pockets of people who can think slow and
come up with relevant new ways of
solving problems and teaching us to be
able to to tune between thinking fast
something slow will be something that I
think you think all right I just wanted
to say we've reached the our point so
many of everyone a closing statement and
then we are gonna stop recording and I
love where this conversation is going
though and I think there's something in
the interplay of like power and
hierarchy and if we can after we stop
recording create a question together for
next week to explore so that we can each
take a turn sharing on that that makes
sense that is a question and then um
come back next week and have this
conversation is I think it's a really
powerful and an important one and I know
I have thoughts on it and if your
closing statements are about it you are
more than welcome so who would like to
go first with their quizzes I'll start
I'll just say and real briefly I'm very
excited it for this I love the way that
this is kind of come together and I
think this is the kind of conversation
that no I look forward to and as you
start to look more at game be a little
bit less of the contentious you know
either/or and more there okay look at
what is it that we're really saying it's
the compass so I'm very grateful for you
putting this together if I can just add
to David's also I'm grateful you know
this is wonderful that we're doing this
and Julie thank you for this again just
to go back to what David was just
mentioning a moment ago is the we have a
system of production extraction in
production so we've got specific rules
that either incentivize or
disincentivize certain extraction of
certain production and so and then based
on that production you either have
access or you don't and if you don't and
even if you do you still need a
distribution system so the thing that
humanities always been fighting for I
think are the rules governing you know
essentially the ownership and the
production part of it and part of the
critique of communism was whether or not
that particular model those guys can
produce enough things in order to
satisfy the demand whatever they can
continue the production they can
continue to incentivize and to have
access and so but the the distribution
part of it I think is is has been
neglected for more than so the the
production part of it the production
part they thought they had the answer of
course they didn't they failed they lost
because they didn't answer the
distribution question after so by not
linking those two they didn't come up
with a good system and so you know I
think we can do both we can have a good
production distribution excuse me good
production system where we can produce
enough things to meet demand and we can
solve the problem of distribution by you
know utilizing a currency in a different
methodology that allows for an open
market but that's not based on the
metrics like we see today who can sell
the most and that's it still the
extraction model meaning if I can just
extract and cut down more trees I'll
make more money right and so as long as
the distribution model doesn't
incentivize that kind of behavior then
we're on the right track so I'll just
leave it there I've just got a couple of
things to say I mean I'm intrigued by
what Brent said earlier on about
coordinating the bottom-up efforts with
the top-down efforts and in the abstract
I absolutely agree with you but the
problem with that idea in my opinion is
that the interests of the bottom-up in
the interest of the top-down are
misaligned at the moment and so there's
no way of coordinating these things
because they're they're interested
fundamentally not in alignment with each
other so much as I like the idea in the
abstract I don't think it really applies
I do think the transition is specially
given what was said earlier about you
know not having actually a clear idea of
what we're trying to transit towards and
therefore can't lay out a clear up
matter what the transition looked like I
come back to what I said earlier about
the idea of experiments small-scale
experiments the
facts of which can be contained right if
they go dreadfully wrong the effects of
them can be contained and the mess
mopped up afterwards you know I mean
without anyone without anyone suffering
sooo badly I would really like to see a
rerun of the kind of experiments Brent
was talking about that we're done back
in the 70s you know if you'd put a
couple of thousand people into a
self-sustaining unit with access to you
know technology and the internet and so
on it's not a bubble right and and see
if those same sort of power dynamics do
start to emerge you know you have
psychologists there as well to guide
people through the process and analyze
what's going on I mean I really think
running these kinds of experiments now
in the light of modern understandings
with you know technology and the ability
to completely alleviate scarcity of all
kinds at least on a small scale like
that I I do think the value in running
these kinds of experiments can't be
overstated and I think that is how the
transition will occur is doing these
things people seeing oh look that really
fucking works let's see if we can scale
that up all that really didn't work
let's see if we can figure out why and
try again you know III think this has
got to be the modality of transition
Brett do you have any closure I think I
would just offer one correction that you
know the you know top-down or elite
strata it's not monolithic right like um
I tried to make the point that there's
lots of factions within that and there's
there's nihilists there's progressives
you know there's there's
well-intentioned people like Bill Gates
who you know mmm critiques can be made
about what their what their impact is
right and and this idea of you know
philanthropy and and the rich kind of
mm-hmm you know buying their way out of
the the problem is is super important
and I just watched an interview from a
month ago of anon geared artists at
Harvard and he was critical of Harvard
while he was there because it's kind of
an image laundering factory right
someone like Jeffrey Epstein can just
donate money to it
and it's a kind of mutually beneficial
relationship but there's a sinister
underbelly to it so we got to address
the root crisis in all of these
situations right and some elites do know
that's why they were open with Anand in
his research and in his public
disclosure of these reality so there's a
kind of a tipping point there and we
need to be clear about what type of lead
ism we we support and want to work with
and participate and and to bring it back
to Bernie Sanders like he's a populist
form of that he is a on every man and I
kind of a blue-collar a kind of
intellectual and leader and I think he's
the right person important I mean he's
the person that's been chosen by the
progressive movement right so when he
announced his candidacy in the last
election it was a long shot but it
surged and you know actually at one
point in the primary kind of matched
Clinton for fur the prospect of winning
you know they all know they're there
polls the poll numbers almost crossed
hmm and there was a lot going on behind
the scenes to that minute deletes those
numbers and that that ultimately stabs
Bernie in the back and then gave the
election to Trump so you know on the
ground we need to be conscious of these
things upfront because I think there was
lots of people in 2016 that saw what was
happening for what it was but they
didn't win they didn't get the the
dominance their voice heard in the
discourse right and I think a lot of
elite establishments like the New York
Times and whatnot they helped you know
kind of you know hand this election to
to a new plutocratic regime in trumpet
and the cabinet that be selected so I
mean the final I don't know what I'm
doing for time but the final point I
would make is just to bring it back to
the time window we have and the long
term historical window of globalization
because like like the you know
geopolitics has
it's own kind of momentum and and
narratives that play out right but we're
at this new junction with the internet
and you know 21st century 4th Industrial
Revolution bringing us together breaking
down those barriers whether we like it
or not right and there's lots of
friction around that but we you know the
only way out is through and to to
rebuild the global order which has been
underfunded and and really hamstrung by
militarism hey so thank you everyone for
coming and participating in this idea
cafe we're gonna try to keep them to an
hour for the game be even though more
study a cafes or half an hour
I know game be a kinko for three hours
seems to be our like average amount for
conversation which I'm pretty much
anything quite honest yeah exactly and
so kind of I like the idea of what we're
gonna do which is kind of creating the
next question based on like where this
one ended off and there's there's energy
around it because I think that figuring
out how to effectively move forward as a
society without hierarchical power down
dynamics is how we create it and so the
more we can play in that space and
figure it out in groups of five and
groups of 20 and groups of 50 in groups
a thousand and figure out how to create
that is what the idea behind the idea
cafe is is to create a platform that
brings together people to have a
conversation and then how do we figure
that out what's working what's not
working and move forward with it so
thanks for coming and participating in
that and we'll say goodbye to YouTube